Guide to the Peter Reddaway Samizdat collection, 1950-2010 GRC0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Peter Reddaway Samizdat collection
Circa 1950s - 2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Reddaway, Peter
GRC0002
70.5 Linear Feet
Samizdat, from the Russian "sam" ("by oneself") and "izdatel'stvo" ("publishing house,") means "self published" and designates prohibited publications created in secret and distributed via underground networks during the Soviet era. The Peter Reddaway samizdat collection contains original samizdat materials from the USSR, samizdat documents copied for distribution by Radio Free Europe/Radio liberty, correspondence, petitions, news sheets, articles, memoirs, works of prose and poetry, published and unpublished book manuscripts, press releases, transcripts of trials, bills of indictment, newspaper clippings and other historical documents. The relevance of the collection goes beyond the study of the Soviet era to encompass the broader study of resistance to totalitarian regimes and dissent more generally. The collection spans the period from mid 1960s to the collapse of the USSR in 1991.
Arrangement
Organized into 11 series: Belle Lettres, Human Rights, Large Manuscript, Mainstream, Nationalities, Psychiatric Abuse, Religious, Radio Free Europe-Radio Liberty (RFE/RL), Social Groups, Western Materials, and Miscellanea.
Biographical / Historical
Peter Reddaway, Professor Emeritus of Political Science and International Affairs of The George Washington University, is a prominent Soviet historian of the Cold War period and a central figure in the Russian samizdat distribution network. He was a prominent advocate of human rights who spoke out on behalf of the oppressed, and a preeminent collector of Soviet samizdat materials. His main scholarly expertise is in the politics and government of Russia and the other post-Soviet states, human rights, rights of minorities, religious freedom and psychiatric abuse. Professor Reddaway received his B.A. and M.A. degrees from Cambridge University and did graduate work at Harvard and Moscow Universities and the London School of Economics and Political Science. Before joining GW in January 1989, he taught at the London School of Economics and then directed the Kennan Institute for Advanced Russian Studies. Professor Reddaway assembled one of the largest private collections of Soviet political samizdat spanning the period from the late 1960s to the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991. Samizdat, from the Russian "sam" ("by oneself") and "izdatel'stvo" ("publishing house") means "self published" and designates prohibited publications created in secret and distributed via underground networks during the Soviet era. These materials were produced at great risk to the individuals and groups responsible for their creation and distribution. But, in the end, ongoing dissent helped to apprise others of conditions within the USSR and supported a coordinated effort to destabilize the authoritarian regime, including the sustained Western effort (by Radio Liberty and other organizations) to broadcast back into the Soviet Union the content of contraband samizdat smuggled out of the USSR. Access to this material, and the associated cultural output essential to substantively interpreting it, is critical to the understanding of the late 20th century and the various ways in which Soviet dissidents resisted the dominant political hegemony. The relevance of the collection goes beyond the study of the Soviet era to encompass the broader study of resistance to totalitarian regimes and dissent more generally.
Scope and Contents
The Peter Reddaway collection contains political samizdat materials from the Soviet Union. It consists of approximately 151 boxes of unique materials or approximately 75 linear feet of materials. This includes thousands of sheets of original samizdat and approximately 27,000 sheets of copied samizdat, English-language translations of samizdat, original samizdat materials from the USSR, samizdat documents copied for distribution by Radio Free Europe/Radio liberty, correspondence, petitions, news sheets, articles, memoires, works of prose and poetry, published and unpublished book manuscripts, press releases, transcripts of trials, bills of indictment, newspaper clippings and other historical documents. It also contains a run of the Chronicle of Current Events in English and in Russian as well as 40 bound volumes of Russian-language samizdat documents compiled by Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty.
The most extensive materials found in the collection relate to the response of Soviet authorities to ideological dissent. These materials include a significant amount of materials focusing on psychiatric abuse, mental health reform and the persecution of religious groups. The collection covers the period from the mid 1960s to the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991, with a few titles extending beyond 1991. Most materials in the collection are in Russian. When possible English translations of the documents are provided. There are documents in the collection in a variety of Western European languages, as well as in languages of the Soviet Republics. Most materials are on paper though there are some photographic negatives in the collection, as well as rolls of photographic film and film strips.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Reddaway, June 23, 2010.
Underground literature -- Soviet Union; Human rights; Samizdat; Freedom of religion; Nationalism; Self-determination, National; Dissenters -- Soviet Union; Political prisoners -- Soviet Union -- Biography; Psychiatry -- Soviet Union; Soviet Union Emigration and immigration; Refuseniks; Jews -- Soviet Union -- Migrations; Jews -- Persecutions -- Soviet Union; Civil rights -- Soviet Union; Women -- Soviet Union -- Social conditions; RFE/RL; Labor movement Russia (Federation); Radio Free Europe; Radio Liberty; People with disabilities -- Soviet Union; Reddaway, Peter
- Belle Lettres, 1970-1973; 1989; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  Contains mostly anonymous works of Russian literature mostly satirical prose fiction, poetry and drama aimed at satirizing Soviet regime and Perestroika.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in the original order provided by the donor
  - Anon[ymous] - Belles-Lettres, 1989 August 04; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anon[ymous] - Belles-Lettres, 1970 December 02-1973 February 19; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Human Rights, 1963-1991; Series 2
  Documents human right abuses and prison camp conditions in the USSR through variety of documents such as articles, letters, reports, statements produced within the country as well as materials produced in the West by the Western supporters of Soviet human rights activists such as translations of documents from USSR, monitoring of Soviet press and press releases.
  Arranged in the original order provided by the donor.
  - H[uman] R[ights] - Official Actions, 1985 June 18-1998 January 18; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Official Documents, 1971 June 28-1984 January 10; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Thuggery, 1973 December 21-1982 May 11; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1974 Western MAT[ERIAL]S - Press + Private Re[:] Dissent [1/2], 1973 August 28-1980 February 19; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1974 Western MAT[ERIAL]S - Press + Private Re[:] Dissent [2/2], 1973 August 28-1980 February 19; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CAMPS REPORT [1/3], 1974 January 13-2013 January 12; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 1)
  - CAMPS REPORT [2/3], 1969 August-1989 September 15; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 2)
  - CAMPS REPORT [3/3], 1965 October 3-1989 September 15; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 3)
  - Dissidents - General, 1985 June 13-1985 November 5; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 4)
  - Human Rights - Theory, 1967 January 11-1971 September; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 5)
  - Human Rights, etc., 1989 July 7-1991 March 17; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 6)
  - I[nternational] P[arliamentary] G[roup For Human Rights In The Soviet Union] Leadership Conference - 1986, 1986 May 24-1986 May 25; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 7)
  - MAT[erial]S for Unpublished Samizdat Anthology, 19 [1/2], 1961 October-1970 March 1; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 8)
  - MAT[erial]S for Unpublished Samizdat Anthology, 19 [2/2], 1963 June 29-1969 December 4; Series 2 (Box 129, Folder 9)
  - Samizdat Vol. 1966 - Unpublished to be in English [1/3], 1964 December 3-1973 December 17; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 1)
  - Samizdat Vol. 1966 - Unpublished to be in English [2/3], 1965 August 20-1968 July 19; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 2)
  - Samizdat Vol. 1966 - Unpublished to be in English [3/3], 1965 May 30-1967 September 22; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 3)
  - SHB I 308 [1/2], 1958-1974 May 27; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 4)
  - SHB I 308 [2/2], 1967 March 30-1973 May 11; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 5)
  - SHB I 309 [1/2], 1963 March 26-1974 October 7; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 6)
  - SHB I 309 [2/2], 1969 July 12-1974 October 7; Series 2 (Box 130, Folder 7)
  - West[ern] Aid to Dissidents' Families 1973, 1970 November-1975 December 11; Series 2 (Box 131, Folder 1)
  - Workers' Strikes, 1989 July 15-1991 March 19; Series 2 (Box 131, Folder 2)
- Large Manuscript, 1963-1994; Series 3
  Contains a variety of manuscripts in handwritten and typewritten form ranging from memoirs to literary prose to scholarly, analytical or journalistic writing, produced unsanctioned Soviet writers and/or political prisoners/human rights activists. Some authors are notorious dissidents while others are lacking any kind of renown. Some are believed to be KGB provocateurs.
  - [Tat'iana] Khodorovich, 1973 January 29-1979 September 9; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Western Corresponedent, 1969 December; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Grigoriev" Zemlya Obetovannaia (I) [1/2], undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Grigoriev" Zemlya Obetovannaia (I) [2/2], undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - [01] Kirja Plokk No. 1 [Tetrad' Pervaia 2.VIII], 1970 August 2; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - [02] Kirja Plokk No.2 [Tetrad' Vtoraia 16.VIII], 1970 August 16; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [03] No.3 [Tetrad' Tret'ia 25.VIII], 1970 August 25; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - [04] No.4 [Tetrad' Chetvertaia 6.IX - 70 g.], 1970 September 6; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - [05] Kirja Plokk T.5 [Tetrad' Piataia 8.XI - 70 g.], 1970 November 8; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - [06] Kirja Plokk T.6 [Pyteshestvie Kniga Pervaia, XI], 1970 November; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - [07] Kirja Plokk 7 [Tetrad' Sed'maia Dekabre 1970 g.], 1970 December; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [08] Kirja Plokk [Tetrad' Vos'maia], 1970 December 13; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [09] Kirja Plokk D.1 [Tetrad' Deciateia], 1963 September-1970 September; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - [10] Kirja Plokk D.2 [Tetrad' Odinnadtsataia], 1963 September-1970 September; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Anat[oly] Butko, 1979-1980 November 17; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - D. Blagov, 1963; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [David] Kowalewski on [Pyotr Grigorevich] Grigorenko [PhD Thesis], undated; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - [Eduard] Kuznetsov, 1970 October 27-1972 March 10; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Grigoriev (II) [1/2], 1971 February 21-1971 November 6; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Grigoriev (II) [2/2], 1971 February 21-1971 November 6; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - [Iaroslav] Karpovich, 1989 July 16-1994 January 3; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - [Krilsky - Samizdat], 1971 October 25-1985 November 9; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Metrapol' Literaturnii Al'manakh [1/3], 1979; Series 3 (Box 150, Folder 1)
  - Metrapol' Literaturnii Al'manakh [2/3], 1979; Series 3 (Box 150, Folder 2)
  - Metrapol' Literaturnii Al'manakh [3/3], 1979; Series 3 (Box 150, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Samizdat, 1963 December 9-1975 March 17; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Obshch[estvennye] Problemy [1/2], 1969 August-1971 December; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Obshch[estvennye] Problemy [2/2], 1969 August-1971 December; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - [Osip] Cherny[i], undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Podrabinek [Aleksander Viktor Nekipelov] (M[anu]S[cript]) [- The Silent Asylum] [1/2], 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Podrabinek [Aleksander Viktor Nekipelov] (M[anu]S[cript]) [- The Silent Asylum] [2/2], 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pol[itical] Diary, 1965 April-1974 October 22; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pol[iticheskii] Dnevnik v.1: nos.3-43 [1/3], 1964 December-1968 April; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pol[iticheskii] Dnevnik v.1: nos.3-43 [2/3], 1964 December-1968 April; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pol[iticheskii] Dnevnik v.1: nos.3-43 [3/3], 1964 December-1968 April; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - R. Medvedev - [Kniga o] Sots[ialisticheskoi] Demokrati[i], 1972; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - [Ragner Tikka], 1969 September 23-1975 October 1; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Romano-Petrova [Nina], undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unlabeled [Reflection on Man - Vasily Chalidze], 1971; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Viktor Pikhtovnikov "prizn" [manuscript], undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Mainstream, Circa 1960s to 1990s; Series 4
  These series contain writings documenting human rights abuses including conditions in prisons and camps and human rights struggle in the USSR during the period spanning decades and different regimes in the country from the Thaw to the end of Perestroika. The series also contains documents pertaining to a very wide variety of human rights organizations in the USSR as well as a long subseries of files on individuals. Taken together, these are virtually a "who's who" in the Soviet dissident movement containing materials on or by individuals involved in the struggle or suffering governmental abuse.
  Organized into six subseries: Anonymous, Bulletin, Collective, Individual, Journal, Miscellanea
  - Anonymous, Series 4 Subseries 1
    - Anon. - St. Prisons and Camps, 1975 September 1-1987 June 15; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Anon. Mainstream and Others [1/3], 1938 August 17-1990 December 14; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Anon. Mainstream and Others [2/3], 1938 August 17-1990 December 14; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Anon. Mainstream and Others [3/3], 1938 August 17-1990 December 14; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Anon[ymous] - re[ference:] Camps and Prisons, 1968 February 20-1976 May 12; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mainstream Anonymous, 1968 December 18-1976 May 9; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin, Series 4 Subseries 2
    - Khronika Press "Information Bulletin" [1/2], 1973 May 5-1976 December 27; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Khronika Press "Information Bulletin" [2/2], 1973 May 5-1976 December 27; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Svobodnaya mysl, 1971 December 20-1972 November 24; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - V Bulletins [Ekhspress Informatsiia], 1983 April-1984 August; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - V-Series 55-69 [1/3], 1980 January 18-1983 April 25; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - V-Series 55-69 [2/3], 1980 January 18-1983 April 25; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - V-Series 55-69 [3/3], 1980 January 18-1983 April 25; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - V-Series up to no.55, 1980 October; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Collective, Series 4 Subseries 3
    - The Democrats [1/2], 1970-1989 March 11; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - The Democrats [2/2], 1970-1989 March 11; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - (1981) Podrabinek on K[irill]P[odrabinek]'s Trial [-Protsess po delu Kirilla Podrabnika, Parizh], Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - [Collective Mainstream], 1968 July 29-1977 May 9; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Collective Mainstream - from Camps and St. Prisons, 1976 October 30-1985 April 1; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Collective Mainstream - Other [1/2], 1969 December 8-1980 December24; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Collective Mainstream - Other [2/2], 1969 December 8-1980 December24; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Coll[ective] Mainstream - Other 1981 -> [1/2], 1981 January 23-1991 May 31; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Coll[ective] Mainstream - Other 1981 -> [2/2], 1981 January 23-1991 May 31; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Collective Mainstream - Programmatic [1/2], 1976 October 14-1991 February 11; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Collective Mainstream - Programmatic [2/2], 1976 October 14-1991 February 11; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Coll[ective] Mainstream "Programmatic", 1964 February 2-1970 April 2; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Collective Mainstream Action Group + Analogous, 1969 May-1972 November 19; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Coll[ective] Mainstream: "R[e:] Trials", 1968 January 20-1972 January 16; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Collective Mainstream From Camps [and St. Prisons] [1/2], 1969 June 28-1976 July 13; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Collective Mainstream From Camps [and St. Prisons] [2/2], 1969 June 28-1976 July 13; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Union, 1988 December 27-1989 January 30; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Group 73 + A[mnesty] I[nternational] Group, 1973 September 1-1976 April 7; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Group 73 and Amnesty International, 1978 October 13-1985 June 20; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Moscow Helsinki Group - Materials about…, 1976 May-1982 September 10; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Moscow Helsinki Group - Numbered Reports [1978] [1/2], 1976 October 12-1978 December 8; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Moscow Helsinki Group - Numbered Reports [1978] [2/2], 1976 October 12-1978 December 8; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Moskow Helsinki Group - Numbered Reports [1978] [1/2], 1979 January 13-1982 September 6; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Moskow Helsinki Group - Numbered Reports [1978] [2/2], 1979 January 13-1982 September 6; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Moskow Helsinki Group - Other Doc[ument]s [1/2], 1976 October 1-1986 February 12; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Moskow Helsinki Group - Other Doc[ument]s [2/2], 1976 October 1-1986 February 12; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Orlov Group - Materials about it, 1976 June 18-1980 November 14; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Orlov Group Numbered Reports, 1976 August 1-1980 August 20; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Orlov Group Other Documents, 1976 May 27-1977 February; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Trust Group, 1982 May 6-1988 September; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Trust Group, 1982 June 5-1985 August 16; Series 4 Subseries 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Individual, Series 4 Subseries 4
    - [Abaev, Vasilii], 1991 November 22; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - [Abalkin, Leonid], 1990 May 18; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - [Ablaev, Eiip], 1979 March 27; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - [Abliamitov, __________ ], undated; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - [Abovin-Egides, P], undated; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - [Abovin-Egides, Petr], 1978 May 18-1979 January 25; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - [Abramkin, Valery], 1977 February 28-1980 October 5; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - [Achte, Kalle], 1977 December 13; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - [Adelheim, Pavel], 1999; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - [Agapova, Liudmila], 1977 January 1-1979 November 12; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Agursky [Mikhail], 1974 July 28-1981 January 22; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Agursky [Mikhail], 1969-1976 April 12; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Agursky [Mikhail], 1972 June 30-1976 May 15; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Aiken'vald, Iurii, undated; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - [Airikian, Paruir], 1980 October 28-1988 July 24; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - [Airikian, Paruir], 1970 February 23-1980 December 30; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - [Akhmetov, Zizametdin], 1969 August 6-1987 March 13; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - [Akhterov, Pavel], 1981 December 24-1982 February 5; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - [Akhterov, Vladimir Tiumily], 1977 September 14-1977 September 14; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - [Aksel'lrod, Ernest], 1977 May 12-1979 September 2; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - [Aksenov, Vasily], 1973 November 30-1984 March 13; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - [Alayan, Allan], 1985 April 19; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Al'brekht [Vladimir], 1983 April 20-1986 August 25; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Al'brekht [Vladimir], 1974-1977 January 21; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - [Aleksandrov, Nikolai], 1970 February 2; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - [Alekseev, Nikolai], 1980 June 23-1981; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - [Alekseeva, Elizaveta], 1980 May 21-1981 November 3; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - [Alekseeva, Ludmila], 1977 March 12-1981 November 3; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - [Alifanov, Oleg], 1985 May 29; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - [Altaev, O. A.], 1972 August 7; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - [Al'tman, A. A.], 1975 May 29; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - [Al'tshuler, Boris], 1977 September 1-1977 December 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - [Altunian, Gemrikh], 1969 October 30-1990 March 13; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Amalrik [Andrej] [1/2], 1967 December 18-1981 January 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Amalrik [Andrej] [2/2], 1967 December 18-1981 January 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - [Amarantov, Boris], 1975 October 7; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - [Amit, Emil], 1982; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - [Amp, Lior], 1986 November 11; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - [Anatol'ev, P.], 1990 March 26; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - [Andreev, Iurii], 1977 January 20-1977 June 26; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - [Andrianova, Irina], 1981 January 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - [Andronova, Elena], 1977 February 13-1978 May 22; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - [Antipenskaia, Mariia], 1978 December 10; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - [Antipov, A.] [pseudonym], 1970 July 15-1970 August 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - [Anti-Tarasov, L.] [pseudonym], 1970 July 16; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - [Antonenko-Davydovych, Borys], 1984 May 25; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - [Antoniuk, Zinovii], 1978 December-1979 June; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - [Antsipov, Evgenii], 1980 July-1986 April 3; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - [Arenberg, Vadim], 1979 June 21; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - [Argentov, Alexander], 1976 July 16-1977 February 9; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - [Arguni, N.S.], 1979 December 25; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - [Arkhangelskii, Vladimir], undated; Series 4 Subseries 4 (Box 16, Folder 16)